let's make a video Let's Make a video
Let's Make a video okay we're recording
so I'm wearing a rocky Linux shirt and
you're going to think this video is
about Rocky Linux it's actually not so
we've been attending the southeast Linux
conference uh By Invitation actually I
had a a friend uh invite me and so I
paid my $25 got this you know one of
many free t-shirts and uh and uh you
know went and checked it out in fact I
don't have any videos of it but um if
you want to check it out you know make
sure you stick around in the IRL Channel
we will be doing it Saturday and Sunday
the question is I mean you go to a Linux
conference one of the the best questions
to ask to to get to know about people
and it's funny because the prime agent
did I say his name right was watching an
an a video on YouTube about what your
Linux Dro says about you so for some
reason you know your Linux drro is kind
of in Vogue right now like a lot of
people are talking about it and so this
morning during morning boost uh I got
asked you know what my favorite drro
was and I said well I don't know for
what based on what which Dr has the best
logo
Dean you see where I'm going there um
and then and then the clarification came
and by the way I'm not picking on you
thank you for asking the question uh the
clarification came for everyday use on
the desktop clinic and I like aha
because
once you know and once you know what
somebody wants to do then you can ask
the dist in fact in fact this is one way
to know whether you should be careful
with a
person I actually I somebody at the
conference is going to see this I had a
couple people come up to me at the
conference like hey I watch your videos
it was nice so I'm going to I'm to to
meet new people which is the reason you
go to conferences you don't go to
conferences to learn anything I mean
really you really don't
um usually the content can be easily and
more accurately uh found online without
going to the conference separate video
about conferences and what I feel about
conferences but so if if the purpose of
a conference is to meet people and hang
out with your friends and things like
that and you know drink a couple beers
maybe get some ideas um uh I they call
it the uh hallway sessions right the
stuff that happens between all the
people that are sharing knowledge uh
that if if that the purpose and one of
the best ways to start up a conversation
is like he so what's your favorite Dro
right and in El lentic convention it's
like asking somebody their FTP at a
cycling convention you know what's your
functional threshold power it's like
it's like the conversation started right
you might as well ask him Point Blank
what's your
religion what what religion are you but
but here's why it's an interesting
question because if they answer
immediately oh Arch Yeah by byar I'm
like oh okay seriously I it I am afraid
of people who answer that question too
quickly because the people the people
who answer the question about what their
distro
is without asking the question well for
what are people that are like laser
focused on you know one particular Dro
because they're dogmatically in love
with the culture of the drro and that is
fine that's fine but I want to know who
I'm dealing with
here kind of in the same vein as like
guy I don't know if I want to talk about
it right now because I'm going to get
myself in trouble
so um yeah anyway somebody that I met at
the convention reminded me
that some people I would rather not hang
out with at a
convention that's all I'm going to say
about that because they might be
watching they might be watching the
subject is a bit dicey this the the
subject okay I was going to suggest
another topic that's even more dicey
than than this to kind of put it in
context yeah so I mean seriously in the
Linux world at a Linux convention asking
someone what their Dro is like what's
your drro Myro is Rocky Linux right I
actually joked with the rocky Linux
people I said I said you know we should
put you and the alma Linux people in a
ring and like charge for tickets and
they're like no no we love each other
and I'm like okay
they probably do they probably do love
them love each other hey how are you
we're making a little video about what's
your favorite Dro so I'm actually going
to answer the
question uh and hopefully it'll be
productive but um and by the way I use
Arch no I do use Arch by the way I do I
do but for what right I use Arch by the
way as a meme if you're new to Linux and
a lot of people watching this have never
even heard this I use Arch by the way is
a meme it's not really a meme it's kind
of a saying and um it's it's become just
a regular practice to say because
because people who and there I'm going
to let you go watch prime review go
Prime has a video it's much better than
mine of of you know having fun with the
video of people talking about what your
your distribution says about you and I'm
going to let you go look up all that
stuff go I suggest you go look at Primes
videos and go go find the video about
what your Dro says about you I'm not
going to link to it or anything um um
but uh in the spirit of staying on topic
with the beginner boost so that you can
make a decision about what dist to use
uh the rest of this video is going to be
about the dros that are out there what
they do what they're for what people
primarily use them for and what I think
you should may be consider them B of
course this is all up to you in the end
uh and so before we actually can embark
on this this adventure of drro
distribution uh and selection we need to
look at uh what are is the
history uh of Linux uh Linux uh
distributions and we're going to do a
little bit of hey there's Mr
tals um and there is an actual image
that I'm looking for I'm doing it the
same way you would do it because I want
to encourage you to do your own research
um so this is the chart that I used to
use a lot I believe it's gotten pretty
dated
though um I don't know though let's see
if we can oh I'm so sorry for the
flashbang and I'm going to turn my my
face off for a second um I'm really
sorry for the flashbang but that's how
this is okay so there are a lot of Linux
distributions uh you know that's G I'll
have you know it's gnu/linux by the way
another meme right it's another meme uh
from that people use to kind of quantify
the pedantic you know members of the
Linux community of which there were many
yesterday at the conference um it's one
of the reasons I don't go to conferences
um um I don't know I just I just don't
anyway so there are a number of Linux
distributions here I'll try really hard
to not get pulled into the history and
stories about each one but I do want to
tell you a little bit about it here's
why because when you know the history of
Linux distributions you can at least um
speak knowledgeably about about your
selection and you can justify it
somewhat if you feel the need a lot of
times you might not but if you're an
architect and you're making decisions
for the company or something like what
should my container distal be what is
you know what what should I do here what
how does this relate to FreeBSD for
example which by the way was represented
at the Linux community at the open
source at the at the the southeast Linux
convention had an entire uh sub
community of of of uh BSD Unix which is
absolutely not Linux um and so anyway so
it's good it's good to know a little bit
of the history and to know where they're
coming from there's tons of material
online for this so this is just my take
on it um so add add one you know one
voice to the rest um so let's actually
go down the major distribution branches
as of 2024 which is when this video has
made so uh the major major categories I
suppose the ancestries are the Debian
based right which includes
ftu um the uh Red Hat based and I would
suggest the Suzie based the slackware
Suzie um now slackware was the one
slackware is the oldest distribution
that's still maintained apparently um I
actually bought slackware in a box in
the 90s um and I bought um mandri which
is a variation of Suzie uh where is
mandri is it mandre
Susie uh back then I don't see it where
oh mandri is a red
hat no it's not oh I guess I was wrong
all this time
no what I don't think this is correct I
think mandri was a Suzie thing anyway
and then you have you have the
do-it-yourself stuff right the Gen 2 and
the and and kind of the arch thing right
so uh the The Rock Linux the Linux from
scratch nobody talks about these but
this Linux from scratch is not a dist by
the way let me just say that again I'm
going to say it to your face Linux from
scratch is not a drro it's a book okay
and if you want to be pedantic and push
back on somebody who's trying to flex
tell them oh he say what dist you I
Linux LPR is a dist it's a
book sip sips coffee oh you're talking
about maybe gen or something
I'm teaching you how to be a pedantic
Castle so anyway text too small can you
zoom in okay I'll
try um I
mean all right let's do this again I'm
sorry sorry for the cough this is this
is live this is live people all right so
here we go deban is at the top here um I
would argue that the two most signicant
this I'm going to get roasted for saying
this but I don't care um the two most
significant distributions are
Debian and red head and you might say
why didn't you say Arch and and the
reason that Arch is not significant I'm
going to say it I'm going to get hate
for the saying so the reason I'm going
to say it
listen there is no such thing as arch in
the
Enterprise there's not and the beginner
boost is about preparing you for actual
jobs and I'm telling you right now
someone if look if you encounter arch in
an Enterprise environment where people
are making regular you know six figure
salaries for doing Linux system
administration or whatever show me a
single company that's using Arch there
are none the only company that I know of
that's using Arch is using it as a drro
to put on like steam deck which is cool
it's really
awesome uh but um Arch people need to
start their own Enterprise and make Arch
the standard yeah there's no company on
the planet that's going to let you run
Arch on your desk I mean a lot of
actually no that's not true I take it
back there are companies that are very
flexible with what you can wear on run
on your own laptop but that's why Arch
is not included why isn't Gen 2 included
Gen 2 is a great distribution if you
want to build your own thing it really
is but you have to compile everything
it's super cool though if you want to
build a distribution get going with it
um
as I said Linux from scratch is a
baseline it's a book about how to do
something and that's usually used if you
want to make your own uh devices or
something right um and I actually prefer
arch for that Arch is really great for
doing I I did I mentioned this uh
another day I I've used Arch to build uh
my own uh security disos so you know a
Dro My Own sort of dro that had its own
thing on it so I would make a virtual
machine
and then I would build it up with Arch
and then I would just clone the virtual
machine anytime I wanted to use it okay
the SC is not sko what sko is not red
hat why is sko here sko's
Unix this this thing has got problems it
does it's got problems um so anyway um
Susie is still very much a thing uh it
it was it's always been more of a German
thing I remember when I first ran Susie
I had um
soua Susie however you want to say it I
had
um uh I couldn't read the installers
because it was in
German uh auntu is a deman distro so
let's get right into it okay so these
days you're mostly going to hear about
two dros Ubuntu and the Enterprise
anyway you're going to hear about
Ubuntu and red
hat those are the only two disos that
matter in the Enterprise period they
really are and
uh you know there's a lot of people that
are going to take issue with that but
they're mostly people that are hobbyists
or uh they're doing other things or
they're streaming or they're building
their own diss or something um the only
the other major
disco uh Linux from scratch is not a Dro
it's a book I keep saying that um so
there's arches on this particular thing
um but you can see there's many many
versions of red hat um wait why did I do
that that was dumb I want to see you
again okay here we go
um so sare is
here um and what's the difference
between red
hat and uh Ubuntu primarily so by the
way um pois is
Ubuntu uh mint is a
buntu and um I mean all of them right um
in the chart next to Rocky Linux yeah
yeah and uh Rocky Linux which is the one
I'm wearing right now is the is my
current favorite
for uh an alternative to red hat which
is a very I'm kind of all over the board
on this but
whatever um which I don't even see here
I don't see Rocky here this is an old it
only goes through 2007 this a really
really old diagram I wonder if there's a
new
one cuz the Centos Centos kind of faded
I don't think Centos is even a thing
again Centos
became that's that's Rock Linux that's
not Rocky Linux
no this chart is dead I got to stop
using it sento was stopped being a thing
and yeah let's see if we can find a
better chart let's see if we can find a
better chart this chart kind of sucks
actually it does now anyway I wonder if
there's a new version of
it um I mean this okay so this this is
actually oh I like this a lot this only
goes through 2007 but this
um I like this because this focuses on
the on the ones that
matter
um
mandre what okay never mind I think I
might have had it wrong let me
distributions all right let's zoom in
all right so that goes through 2008 so
Dean to auntu auntu goes to to to Pap
and M and all that uh SL goes to
slackware I didn't realize suie was a
for slacker I didn't realize that that's
cool uh that's still really big red hat
goes to sento which is the open source
version Red Hat Enterprise and you guys
know the IBM bought Red Hat uh pretty
much destroyed it um even though red hat
is still the leader uh red hat is also
leading the the world in uh the open sh
shift you know kubernetes deployments to
the entire world um redhead is a
significant company whether or not you
like them does not
matter um they are the most significant
distribution for running uh Linux on
hardware and I I'll go to the Grave on
that H you nine times out of 10 if you
ask somebody who's in the Enterprise and
they've deployed Linux on millions of
machines they're going to tell you that
they're running
hat and so why why would I be interested
in Rocky U so
sentos stopped being a thing I don't
want to get into it uh I think it got
resurrected again though so so now we
have sentest Elma Elma Lin Elma Linux
and uh Rocky Linux and Elma and Rocky
are kind of they both so I think it was
two years ago cinta was sort of died and
everybody was like oh no we need a free
and open Enterprise red hat and that was
when Rocky and Elma were born and I've
I've actually done uh some rocky
installs and I know I think Tannis does
some rocky installs um and Fedora core
has always been a thing uh I sold my red
hat stock in 200 something when Red Hat
split uh into Fedora what they do is
they have Fedora is the free version of
red hat without all the extra enterpris
kind of thing
and uh they take commits to the Fedora
core and then they put them into their
Enterprise version and make their
Enterprise version better uh people that
hate red hat hate him because they are
making gobbles and gobbles of money
oodles and oodles of money not Gobles
what am I thinking about they make tons
of money because of a bunch of Open
Source contributions and that really
really angers open- Source people um and
I don't want to chime in on that other
than to say that that's just how it is
um I I've I readed hat the one of the
main distinctions between by the way
between these distributions is the type
of package uh manager and and system
that you're using so uh I'm going to say
that again so one of the the core
distinctions between a distribution is
the method of distribution and the
method of updating and so uh for auntu
you have
a um you know the package manager it's
called the package manager package is
like the application is packaged up
right or whatever and then that's
installed so so auntu has AP which is
widely considered easier to use than all
the other ones um that's why buntu leads
the field in
containerization uh when when you need
to install Linux into a container um
image they people really for one to
there's it's kind of funny that they
didn't list Alpine at all um which is I
mean that's such an important dist and
it's not even here um okay suszie has
its own
installer uh and red hat has its own
inst RPM uh actually it's not it's yum
these days so the main thing to take
away from that is that that Linux
distributions uh beyond their logos are
usually distinguished by how they're
installed
and you're probably if you're out on the
Internet or on YouTube people are going
to tell you that they're distinguished
by you know what their desktop
environments are and things like no the
fundamental difference between the
distributions is how they manage the
software um and what software comes by
default and the installer um so the
installer and how the software gets in
you know put onto this that's what
installer is those that's the other part
of it um so these are the major
distributions um and we will be doing uh
auntu we'll be doing uh installing auntu
into auntu server uh I think it's
important to note too that that
um that you've
got uh I mean quite a difference
between um you got quite a difference
between server and desktop right some of
these don't even have a desktop version
uh and I think that that's an important
distinction too so
uh I'm just reporting to you what is out
there uh I mean you can do your own
research here here's another one this is
this is this is much crazier I bet click
to enlarge 404 not found engine
X yeah that's a broken image um what
else we got here anyway so this video
has gone much longer than I wanted to um
I'm still going to keep it though you
guys can find it there obviously are
YouTubers who focus on
distributions um the only distributions
that matter and I mean it the only
distributions that matter from the sense
of of of of what's going on the only
ones that matter are uh Ubuntu and red
hat and if you only needed to learn two
dros uh that would be
Arch doesn't matter you can learn it
it's cool you'll learn a lot about Linux
but it doesn't matter you're not it's
not going to help you get a job if you
want to learn Red Hat you're going to be
looking at something like Rocky Linux
because you're going to have to install
that if I were you I would stick with
red hat or rocky or some some variation
of it to learn uh Hardware so red you
know how to how does Linux run on
hardware and that would include um
potentially you know your servers
particularly Red Hats designed primarily
for servers software so I mean it's
that's someone's going to get really mad
at me obviously they have a desktop as
well but so what I would do is I would
like buy one or two computers cheap ones
and put Rocky Linux on them and then get
good with that figure out how to do that
how do you network them and all that
stuff in your lab that that would be my
recommendation and then in addition to
that I would buy a very very cheap
laptop we were at Micro Center yesterday
and there there
killer Acer laptops there for
$150 Asus and Acer make really good
laptops for distributions for making a
Linux distribution uh or installing one
and I would install uh either poos which
has done me wrong I met the 70 system 76
guys yesterday and they seem really good
and they seem like they've come a long
way I actually am pretty impressed by
their their rust desktop that they've
redone um I mean if there's one thing
you're going to that rust would be good
at it's and fast at it's you know
rewriting the desktop and so they they
they basically have thrown gnome out the
window it'll still do gnome stuff but
and now they put that on there so if
you're looking for a desktop Dr which is
its own thing so getting a laptop and
then putting a desktop Dr on there and
trying out all the favorites in fact
when I used to do I have a story about
this because I used to have I would give
beginners an Asus and take them home and
say put whatever Linux on there you want
to and they would install everything and
people would land on on Susie I'm not
kidding there's a couple a couple of
people that I helped and they decided
that they wanted to use Su on their
desktop uh there's a lot of them that
like monjaro until it went Belly Up and
totally died on them and then they
literally came crying I broke my
computer how can I get it fixed I'm so
sorry Mr Rob and I'm like that was M
that was mararo not you know so your
desktop Linux but my suggestion is that
you stick with an obuntu Debian based
Linux laptop that's my recommendation
you do whatever you want the reason for
that is because it's easier to maintain
uh you're you're going to be getting
good with all the same commands that you
use for containerization later in your
career and um that lets you use red hat
on your servers now a lot of people will
still put a bunch of server on their
Hardware I in my lab I had a bunch of
Sera because I didn't want to have to
deal with you know marrying the two
distribution types uh particularly if
you're doing like um an air gapped lab
where you have to bring down the
packages and stuff like that and set up
you know server to to cach them and
everything um so that's my
recommendations um I still strongly
recommend Linux Mint um I'm right on the
fence right now between recommending
Linux Mint and papos um and uh a quick
story about Pap um those that been
watching me stream for a while know that
in 2020 2021 actually when I started
streaming uh a member really early
member of my community haven't been back
since then but somebody named viable
Clan member recommended I use Papa West
and that they were using Papa West
everywhere this was in 2020 and uh 2019
actually and I started using it I was
like well fine let's try it so I started
using po I made poest the standard for
my lab and for all my community I
started recommending it to everybody and
fast forward this was after mjara I put
mararo on all the lab systems and it
broke it bricked it seriously it bricked
my lab I had to go in and re reimage my
lab
uh and I reimaged it with Linux Mint
because it's never failed me it's really
boring but it really never failed me um
and then I found out about Pap let we
put Pap on and then I streamed with Pap
I was actually streaming from Pap on the
desktop for 2020
2021 I think through
2022 and then it finally died in fact I
booted uh I booted I booted Papa and my
screen was black and I was really happy
that I had set up SSH to my my desktop
because I had to SSH from an an external
machine to get in to save my files and
stuff off there I couldn't even boot
into the non-graphical mode I it was it
was really bad and and I don't know what
happened I think I might have had auto
update on or something but I it was you
can say user error all you want
everybody loves to just say this um but
no it just died and I and when that I I
never wanted to use it after that after
that I never used it because I I cannot
deal with non stabil non-stable dist
Linux men is is boring but doesn't f
doesn't fail like a Volo M says there
there are a lot of people and and they
the characterization you know I felt
really seen in the video uh that Prime
was playing about about what your Linux
distri says about you and they they they
did you use IC mintt and it had it had a
it had a dad wearing New Balance and
khakis you know turning his his hot dogs
on his barbecue you know you know with
the with the dad glasses and everything
he was like yeah he was totally
boring you know and uh the user eror
people yeah there's a lot of people like
that so um so I've my official
recommendation is still Linux Mint to a
beginner uh because it's never done me
wrong and and when you're a beginner you
don't want a lot of things you don't
want a lot of variation um however I I
am tempted to try poos the reason I like
poos is because it is such a simple OS
it's so beautifully
designed um from a an absolute beginner
perspective it's extremely beginner
friendly they've had really great
designers participate in the creation of
Po desktop and and it it might be worth
a try again when I found out they were
rewriting gnome in
Rust I kind of got turned off by that
honestly um but after having met the
system 76 guys yesterday and after you
know having them show me the new beta
rust desktop that they're running it's
basically I3 plus gnome and it does the
whole scrolling thing with the
three-finger scrolling like Max do um
and it is smooth I mean it is smooth and
fast even on relatively mediocre
Hardware system 76 Hardware but I I'm
hopeful I'm hopeful I'm gonna I'm going
to put it out there I think I I truly
believe that that if they can pull this
off that might actually be one of the
better rust applications out there and
that's having said that I I was an El
laity user for two years alacrity is the
rest terminal and then I found that they
didn't Implement full support for all
the ansy uh the ask the ansy character
sets including um you know colors and
blink and all the other things that are
supported by all the other Terminals and
we'll talk about terminals
later but but that that is my
recommendation so so if you're a
beginner and you're you I you know buy a
cheap laptop we're going to talk about
that but and then put either popos or
Linux Mint on there and that's my
recommendation you can do of course
whatever you want and the really great
thing about Linux is is There's No No
Boundaries you can do whatever you want
just be sure that you know and you're
not going to break anything you really
aren't I said break laptop but you can't
you can't you can't break it right you
cannot break it uh here's another
comment AG greed been using mint for
three years without issues uh yeah so
especially if you are um if you're come
if you're coming into and by the way I
didn't mention C Linux which we should
probably mention um Cali Linux is a uh
as I understand it it's an extension of
knopic actually uh it's one of those
security it was a security Dr it came
right from the same people who made
knopic and all those other kind of
things this this this is the only Dr
that used to come on a CD you used to be
able to boot a CD and KNIX was was
really cool for helping um you know
debug systems even Windows machines I
actually brought a bunch of Windows
machines back to life booting into
knopic off the disc and going and
getting the files off there and they
always thought I was a wizard for being
able to recover their their broken
Windows machine um and so that then that
grew into many other dis and then
ultimately to C I don't know the exact
path but C is not a bu to C is its own
Beast um it still uses AP package
manager though so it has the same as as
Debian uh some of you remember opix opix
was like uh thank you um so um but but
yeah so that that that might be fun for
you to look at actually running I mean
these days you can boot from a USB and
into pretty much anything backtrack with
then Cali yeah that was it so it was it
was KNIX and then backtrack and then
Cali and and so that's been a but they
use AP package manager which can confuse
you because it feels a lot like a buntu
right when you're doing install when
you're doing um when you're doing when
you're when you're doing installations
and stuff like that um so so that is
look you can try dist what I I talked
about the laptop I talked about the
server uh for the Bruce we're going to
do a lot of virtual machine stuff and
run a virtual machine if you got enough
hard if you got enough you know ump in
your power in your laptop or whatever
you can run a bunch of these Linux
distal in a BM that's what I do on this
Windows machine right now and whether
it's a server or a desktop you can do
that and you can actually do quite well
um depending on how if you have Modern
Hardware or not uh it was notx backtrack
H and parrot yeah there par parrot as
well parro is another uh there are a lot
of security dis Ros um parrot C
um oh God what's the other one there's a
Gen 2 based one too I can't remember it
though uh right now anyway uh the
security dros is is a different topic
altogether uh if you're going to go into
security you know they generally have
use Cali to start out with but if you're
going to do that the good hackers
usually don't use Cali we're talking
like the really good ones we're talking
they usually build their own
disos um and they don't put a lot of the
bloat and in there they only they only
pick the tools that they want and
actually one of the things that turned
me off uh from cyber security in general
uh yeah Cali is maintained by offensive
security and it's also required uh if
you're going to certify there's there's
actually a free certification in Cali
Linux uh that you can get from ocp for
for the for just Cali Linux um if you're
going to you know go into the security
uh
space
um so yeah use Cali go I I'm I was kind
of remiss not even mentioning it because
it is you know people watch me who do
security stuff um you know I I think
it's great if you want to pop something
up in a VM and put it over VPN and start
doing your thing that's fine um I would
encourage you eventually though to to
get away from
c um I would start to build your own
drro and actually Gen 2 is really good
for that uh Arch and Gen 2 J Gen 2 you
have I mean if you watched last mile
last miles is building with Gen to all
the time because you literally are
compiling your own pieces of a distro
Linux from scratch is more for people
that want to do embedded systems and
they want to start by customizing their
own Linux kernels um which is a totally
low-level amazing cool thing to do but
you know it's unless you're going to go
into computer
engineering uh you might not want to go
down that rout and you certainly don't
want to go there if you're a beginner if
you're an absolute beginner um you know
I would stay with you know putting
putting uh auntu or some flavor of auntu
on your laptop and sticking with red hat
for your servers for now and and
sticking with C uh or parrot in in a VM
for cyber security um so well let's
amend that um because if you're doing
cyber security you have to have C so so
C in a VM by the way don't do you have
to have a BM for Cali Linux right almost
I've never even Mr Robot Elliot you know
he'll he'll boot up he doesn't boot up
and he'll sometimes he'll dual boot but
most of the time you want to be him
anyway because it's going to protect you
right you're going you're not going to
be doxing as much about yourself if
you're hacking if you're running from a
VM seriously like you know just just run
your hacking stuff from a VM all right
so and that's what C is good for but
it's even better if you like build your
own VM dist like I said so you can take
Arch you can take all your favorite
purses pieces off of there and and stick
them into AR get them all you know and
then you can save off your snapshot uh
we'll talk about VMS but I don't know
about snapshotting or not I think that's
all free now by the way VMware has made
snapshotting uh unlimited free which was
not a thing last year so so you got Cali
Linux for the security uh you have some
a bunto based just for your laptop on
your Hardware um and containers a bun of
server for containers and then you have
red hat server uh for your servers and
that that's that's my recommendation
um and that's all for this video